Guide to the Shenandoah Valley Oral History Project, 2005-2009: SdArch 29
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
- Series 2: Oral History Interviews, 2006–2009
  - 29-58: Lohr, Matthew, interviewed by Matthew Lohr, April 12, 2007
    - Preservation master, April 12, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-096)
  - 29-59: Luebben, Carl, interviewed by John Erdos, October 24, 2008
    Records an interview with Carl Luebben, an inspector working for the USDA Service Center and District Office in Harrionburg Virginia. Luebben discusses changes agriculture in the region, and problems associated with increasing concentrations of poultry and livestock in Rockinham County. He discusses the history of fertilizer composition and fertilizer-use in the Shenandoah Valley, the relationship between fertilizer use and soil quality, no-till, mergers of various fertilizer companies, hardpan and soil compaction, water quality, Farm Bureauc Federation. Luebeen dicusses the discovery of high levels of coliform and other pollutants in the Muddy Creek Watershed during the mid-1990s, and efforts to address those concerns with area farmers. Luebben discusses Old Order and Mennonites who are facing land constraints, as their communities increase in size, and his experiences working with Mennonite and Old Order farmers.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, October 24, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Original audio-disc, October 24, 2008 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-052)
    - Preservation master, October 24, 2008 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-092)
  - 29-60: Manka, John, interviewed by Tyler Maupin, September 28, 2008
    Records an interview with John Manka, a park ranger at the Shenandoah National Park. Manka discusses the history and creation of the park. He discusses the diaplacement of and relocation of park residents, various populated areas in the park, such as Nickelson Hollow area and Big Meadows, the establishement of relocation centers for displaced people, and various livelihoods including tanbarking, orchards and fruit-trees, raising livestock, and moonshining. He discusses efforts to learn more about Native American peoples presence on what is now park land, including the Monacan tribe. He discusses the history of Skyline Drive and the work of the Civilian Conservation Corp (CCC); the mission schools built by the Episcopal church in the Blue Ridge Mountains; various ecological topics, including native plants, efforts to establish the chestnut, the threat of fires and blights, invasive species, and efforts to re-introduce certain wildlife. He discuses the impact of tourism on the park, funding, and personal reflections about the work of being a park ranger.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, September 28, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Original audio-disc, September 28, 2008 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-053)
    - Preservation master, September 28, 2008 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-095)
  - 29-61: Mason, James L., interviewed by Daniel Kerr and HIST 337 Class, February 26, 2008
    - Transcript and supporting documents, February 26, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Preservation master, February 26, 2008 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-094)
  - 29-62: May, Betty and Martha Ringwald, interviewed by Heather Crabtree, March 16, 2007
    Records an interview with Betty May, Harrisonburg resident who discusses her twenty-three year career in the poultry industry. Betty May is deaf and the interview occurred with interpreter, Martha Ringwald. May discusses various topics including jobs she had while working at the Cargill plant, changing demographics of her co-workers, mechinization, breaks, pay, physical pain from the work, uniform and dress code, and communicating with others.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 16, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Original audio-disc, March 16, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-054)
    - Original audio-disc, March 16, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-055)
    - Preservation master, March 16, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-092)
  - 29-63: Mehegan, James O., interviewed by John Profita, March 16, 2007
    Records an interview with James O. Mehegen, poultry grower and breeder in Harrisonburg, Virginia. Mehegen owns a breeder facility, and contracts with George's (formerly Rocco) to raise chickens; working as a child on his dad's poultry farm; the labor demands of raising breeders vs. broilers; record-keeping responsibilities; composting dead birds; collecting eggs; poultry feed and fuel demands; farm safety; changes in technology; difficulties working with integrated poultry companies; and his Christian faith.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 16, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Original audio-disc, March 16, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-056)
    - Preservation master, March 16, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-093)
  - 29-64: Metzler, Martha Garibay, interviewed by Abigail Eisley, April 9 and 13, 2009
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 9 and 13, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Original audio-disc, April 9 and 13, 2009 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-057)
  - 29-65: Michael, Donald, interviewed by Sean Maher, November 22, 2008
    Records an interview with Donald Michael, who discusses his cattle and poultry business in the Shenandoah Valley. Michael discusses various topics, including poultry litter fertilizer and nutrient management plans; veterinarian costs; fuel prices; nutritional content of the various grasses; mineral supplements; registered angus and cross-breed cows; rotational grazing; contracting poultry growing for Georges; embryo transfers and artificial insemination; stockyards; buying and selling cattle; farm subsidies; using donkeys and Great Pyrenese dogs; erosion; the use of growth hormones in cattle; increasing cost of production; and the relationship with your banker.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, November 22, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Original audio-disc, November 22, 2008 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-058)
    - Preservation master, November 22, 2008 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-093)
  - 29-66: Miller, Charles W., interviewed by Tim Van Shaik, April 12, 2007
    Records an interview with Charles W. Miller of Bridgewater, Virginia. Miller discusses various topics related to his work in the poultry industry including how poultry growing has changed over time; the transition from free range to confinement houses; the impact of automated waterers and feeders; poultry diseases, including cholera; poultry litter and waste management; composting dead turkeys; hatcheries; turkey breeds, including bronze and white turkeys; involvement with the Shenandoah Valley Gem and Mineral Society in Dayton; decision to grow for the Shenandoah Valley Poultry Growers Cooperative (VPGC), as opposed to Pilgrim's Pride or Cargill; decision to grow for for various companies, including Wampler and Rocco; growout houses; feed; ventilation and the use of fans; his frustrations with regulations from the companies; turkey odor and impact on neighbors; free trade and farm subsidies; his views on imported goods and welfare (SdArch-29-67).
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 12, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Original audio-disc, April 12, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-059)
    - Preservation master, April 12, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-092)
  - 29-67: Miller, Forrest, interviewed by Mary Catherine Collins, April 3, 2007
    Records an interview with William Forrest Miller, of Bridgewater Virginia, and his work as a trucker and farmer on a multi-generational family farm. Discusses his grandfather's orchard and fruit trees, and his father's poultry business; the transition from raising turkeys on free range to confinement houses; his role on the Board of Directors of the Virginia Poultry Growers Coop (VPGC); turkey genetics and breeding; poultry diseases, respiratory problems and the avian flu outbreak in 2002; the beginnings of the VPCG; his cattle business, trucking company, poultry litter business; environmental regulations and water quality; the Chesapeake Bay Foundation; nutri-managment plans; various approaches to fertilizers and fertilizing; changes in feeding and equipment; his interest in other farming ventures; and Mennonites who raise poultry on a small-scale.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 3, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Original audio-disc, April 3, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-060)
    - Preservation master, April 3, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-094)
  - 29-68: Osorio, Rene and Janet, interviewed by Sean Dougherty, December 12, 2006
    Records an interview with Jose Osorio, with his daughter, Janet Osorio translating from Spanish. Osorio discusses his life in Oaxaca, Mexico and Mexico City, and his previous work in a green house. Osorio discusses his current work at the Cargill processing plant in Harrionsburg, Virginia, and covers various topics including the work uniform; sanitation; USDA inspections, benefits, health insurance and job security; a situation where he almost lost his job for taking an antibiotic; sanitation; pay and pay raises; workplace safety measures, and accidents he has witnessed at the plant; conflicts between the line leaders and the line workers; the experience of using an interpreter at work; training programs offered by Cargill; and his decision to move to Harrisonburg.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, December 12, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Original audio-disc, December 12, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-061)
    - Preservation master, December 12, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-097)
  - 29-69: Patton, Richard, interviewed by Christina Wulf, November 14, 2008
    Records an interview with Richard Patton, Forest Hydrologist at the George Washington and Jefferson National Forests. Patton describes his work doing environmental analysis, water quality monitoring and stream restoration. Patton discusses topics including his education; the history of the North River District geology; acidification from acid rain and the problem of acidified streams; filtration capacity of the soil; Switzer Dam as a flood control dam; drinking water reservoirs including Staunton Dam and Elkhorn Dam; Harrisonburg drinking water supply; various flooding events; dam construction; the relationship between the Forest Service and the city of Harriosnburg; reservoir use; George Washington Protection Plan; the impact of tha dam on fisheries and adaquatic life; sedimentation and the impact of sediment size on aquatic life; various waterways in the North River District and their uses; and the impact of timber harvesting on streams.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, November 14, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Original audio-disc, November 14, 2008 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-062)
  - 29-70: Preston, Rob, interviewed by Carole Ryan, October 25, 2006
    Records an interview with Rob Preston, poultry farmer in Harrisonburg, Virginia. He discusses being first-generation farmer; raising male turkeys; poultry feed; one-stage flocks; adjusting to environmental changes; litter storage and disposal; transportation provided by the co-op and integrators; automation of fans and ventilation in the turkey houses; biosecurity, poultry diseases, and precautions to prevent cholera outbreaks; changes in turkey growing time; and the shift from raising bronze turkeys to white turkeys.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, October 25, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Original audio-disc, October 25, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-063)
    - Preservation master, October 25, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-097)
  - 29-71: Processing Worker 1, interviewed by Kerry Gorey, March 16, 2007
    Records an interview with an anonymous woman who worked for Rocco poultry plant in Harrisonburg, Virginia, for 17 years. She describes growing up in Mexico; moving to the United States when she was a teenager; her work in the evisceration department; attending safety meetings; a situation when human resources called a meeting and said they would be fired if they tried to unionize; challenges related to training; inspections; supervisors; her involvement with the Covenant Prebyterian Church.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 16, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Original audio-disc, March 16, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-064)
    - Preservation master, March 16, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-098)
  - 29-72: Randall, Susan, interviewed by Matthew Neese, April 23, 2007
    Rrecords an interview with Sue Randall, who runs a Elk Run Farm, in Fort Defiance, Virginia. Randall has a 30 acre farm where she raises free-range chickens and Boer goats, and grows vegetables and herbs. Randall describes various farm tasks, including fencing and netting the chickens, cleaning the chicken house, composting, and collecting and cleaning the eggs. She discusses how goats and chickens are good partners, hand-raising her goat, Marlin, and working with her Great Pyranese guard dog.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 23, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Original audio-disc, April 23, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-065)
    - Preservation master, April 23, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-097)
  - 29-73: Rezai, Osman, interviewed by Dan Brennan, March 20, 2009
    Records an interview with Osman Rezai who operates a clothing shop in Harrisonburg, Virginia. Rezain describes his life experiences, including growing up in the Kurdistan province of Iran, and the difficulties faced by Kurdish people; his work for the Kurdish military and humanitarian work; the events that lead to him and his family immigrating to Iraq, Turkey, and finally seeking refugee status to enter the United States; and the Kurdish community in Harrisonburg, Virginia,
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 20, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Original audio-disc, March 20, 2009 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-066)
    - Preservation master, March 20, 2009 (Box 1, Cd-r SA029-cd-097)
  - 29-74: Royer, Adam, interviewed by Heather Crabtree, April 6, 2007
    TRANSCRIPT INCOMPLETE. Records an interview with Adam Royer, who worked for the Wampler poultry plant from 1996 until 2001. Royer describes growing up as a triplet, and his experiences with epilepsy. Royer began work while he was in high school and held various roles, including work in the supply room, on the line, cleaning the floors, and eventual transfer to the Broadway plant. He describes the circumstances of his firing and subsequent employment. Royer is married to Samantha Royer (see SdArch 29-75).
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 6, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Original audio-disc, April 6, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-067)
    - Preservation master, April 6, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-097)
  - 29-75: Royer, Samantha, interviewed by Ali Womack, April 17, 2007
    Records an interview with Samantha Royer, who worked for Pilgrim's Pride Poultry plant in Harrisonburg, Virginia. Royer describes her work as a computer operator, including topics such as machine maintenance; overtime pay, vacation and benefits; safety concerns, the demographics of her coworkers; conflict with co-workers and concerns about inappropriate behavior; OSHA; the practice of firing and rehiring at base pay; changes to the company when Wampler (WLR) sold to Pilgrim's Pride; her extended family's involvement with the poultry industry; her views of supervisors and management; her interest in studying business administration. Samantha is married to Adam Royer (SdArch 29-74).
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 17, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Original audio-disc, April 17, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-068)
    - Preservation master, April 17, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-092)
  - 29-76: Ruvalcaba, Evelio, interviewed by Ali Womack, March 23, 2007
    Records an interview with Evelio Ruvalcaba, of Harrisonburg, Virginia. Ruvalcaba discusses his childhood in Colotlan, Jalisco, Mexico, where his family worked on a farm; working in Odell, Oregon to pick apples; his work at Chili's and a poultry plant in Harrisonburg, Virginia; his family in Mexico; and his views on living in Harrrisonburg. Ruvalcaba describes his work at the poultry plant, including the assembly line; management; what it takes to advance; compensation; safety issues; and workplace conflict.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 23, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Original audio-disc, March 23, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-069)
    - Preservation master, March 23, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-094)
  - 29-77: Salatin, Joel, interviewed by Jessica Silvery, April 21, 2007
    Records an interview with Joel Salatin, a farmer and owner of Polyface Farm, in Swoope, Virginia. He describes his father and mother's experiences farming in Venezuela and their return to the United States following civil unrest; his father's efforts to get compensation their farmland; his relationship with the journalist Drew Pearson; selling eggs as a ten-year-old at a market in Staunton; his views on sustainability, stewardship, and eating seasonally; childhood involvement in 4-H; work for the Staunton newspaper in high school; the beginnings of Polyface farm. Salatin discusses the poultry and meat production, including biosecurity; Marek's disease and chicken health; poultry feed; the decision to not to gain organic certification; relationship to local economy; benefits of free-range chickens; relationships with other farmers in the area; industrialized food systems; his employees and his commitment to hiring locally; processing chickens on the farm; regulations and testing; bacteria; his views on farmers' ethical and moral obligations; his view on the future of food.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 21, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Original audio-disc, April 21, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-070)
    - Preservation master, April 21, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-095)
  - 29-78: Sampson, Sarah B., interviewed by Kristy Kendall, February 26, 2008
    Records an interview with Sarah B. Sampson of Harrisonburg, Virginia. Sampson describes her experiences in Harrisonburg, including moving to Harrisonburg in the early 1960s; attending Lucy Simms where she played basketball and other sports; the "urban renewal" movement in Harrisonburg and the impact on the Northeast neighborhood; her mother-in-law's experience of relocating to a development; experiences of racism, First Baptist Church and church experiences; the Bundy Boys; school integration. Sampson describes former businesses in Harrisonburg, including stores owned by Joseph and Alfred Neys, Woolworth's, Denton's furniture store, Leggett's, and the Colonnade. She is a member of the the NAACP.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, February 26, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Preservation master, February 26, 2008 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-097)
  - 29-79: Saylor, Justina, interviewed by Ali Womack, April 10, 2007
    Records an interview with Justina Saylor of Harrisonburg, Virginia regarding her work at the Cargill Distribution Center. Saylor describes driving a forklift, work in the freezer, hours and overtime work, vehicle training, benefits, demographics of coworkers, management, and shipping, among other topics.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 10, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Original audio-disc, April 10, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-071)
    - Preservation master, April 10, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-095)
  - 29-80: Sayre, Brent, interviewed by Mary Catherine Collins, March 12, 2007
    Records an interview with Brent Sayre, a poultry farmer from Mount Crawford, Virginia. Sayre describes his experiences in the poultry industry, including his family history; raising brooder chickens for Rocco, Inc. and later George's; his education; the challenges of being self-employed; growing seasons; building additional poultry houses; ventilation systems including tunnel ventilation and vapor systems; working with George's; end market buyers and fast food; biosecurity and poultry disease such as avian flu; litter movement, nutrient management plans, and regulations regarding litter disposal and use; Virginia Department of Environmental Quality (DEQ) initiatives; competition and relationships with other poultry gorwers; cleaning the poultry houses; using peanut hulls for shavings; Valley Proteins; and dairy farming.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 12, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Original audio-disc, March 12, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-072)
    - Preservation master, March 12, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-092)
  - 29-81: Showalter, Marlan, interviewed by Caitlin Boyer, November 11, 2008
    Records an interview with Marlan Showalter, farmer at Portwood Gardens in Dayton, Virginia. Showalter describes growing up on a multi-generational farm, his father's dairy farm and vegetable farm, Nutrient Film System (NFT) for growing plants hydroponically, his work for a geological survey at Mt. Sidney, the coal furnace and radiator used for heating the greenhouses, harvesting lettuce and selling to Harrisonburg city and Rockingham county schools, challenges of getting permits for the green houses, zoning laws, hydroponics water use, radiant floor heat, plans for aquaponics, and introducing the bermundi fish to hydroponic operation.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, November 11, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Original audio-disc, November 11, 2008 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-073)
    - Preservation master, November 11, 2008 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-096)
  - 29-82: Sites, Debbie, interviewed by Abigail Eisley, March 24, 2009
    Records an interview with Debra (Debbie) Sites, of Harrisonburg, Virginia. Debbie discusses a wide range of topics, including her family and childhood; past work in poultry plants, fast food, nursing homes and other work; her time living at Our Community Place (OCP) in Harrisonburg; her conversations with city and county officials; various soup kitchens in the Harrisonburg area; homelessness; health; her experience at the Salvation Army, First Step, Blue House and Harrisonburg and Rockingham Thermal Shelther (HARTS); housing availability in Harrisonburg; disability conpensation, food stamps, and Medicaid; transportation and the bus system in Harrisonburg; cooperation with others; her conversation with Don Driver, Director of Social Services in Harrisonburg-Rockingham County; involvement of James Madison University students at OCP; her views on Harrisonburg population growth; the Community Services Board (CSB).
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 24, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Original audio-disc, March 24, 2009 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-074)
    - Preservation master, March 24, 2009 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-093)
  - 29-83: Stoneburner, Dennis and Robert Huffman, interviewed by Richard F. Jones, April 15, 2007
    Records an interview with Dennis Stoneburner, a poultry grower, and Robert Huffman, owner of Glenn Hill Farm in Broadway Virginia. Stoneburner and Huffman discuss various topics including their partnership; multiple businesses including poultry, raising cattle, bailing hay and selling poultry litter compost; partnering with Tyson to build grow houses in the late 1970s and 1980s; changes in turkey grow time, feed, breeds and watering systems; static pressure machines; avian flu; concerns that the poultry industry will move to the midwest; consolidation within the poultry industry; Rocco, Inc. and Wampler; vertical integratation; barbecue chicken; rising expenses in fuel, LP gas, wood shavings and feed; and the Holly Farms incident in 1989.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 15, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Original audio-disc, April 15, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-075)
    - Preservation master, April 15, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-093)
  - 29-84: Strickler, Robert H. (Twig), interviewed by Jessica Woodward, April 23, 2007
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 23, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 1)